Federico Fabio Frattini

☑: frattinf@tcd.ie☑: @FedFabFrat□: +353872172669

(b): Personal Website **in**: Linkedin Profile

I am a PhD candidate in Economics at Trinity College Dublin, where I am working on research projects related to political economics and the economics of crime, with an applied-micro approach and a focus on causal inference. I am also passionate about coding, programming languages and statistical software. I am curious, a hard worker, with an analytical mindset prone to problem-solving. I am based in Dublin but I am planning to relocate to Italy.

Education

Ph.D., Economics, Trinity College Dublin, September 2018-(Expected) September 2022

Thesis title: "Essays in Political Economics"

Supervisor: Nicola Mastrorocco

M.Sc., Economics, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, 2015-2017

Supervisor: Massimo Bordignon

B.Sc., Economics and Management, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, 2011-2015

Supervisor: Salvatore Piccolo

Work Experience

Trinity College Dublin, September 2018 -(Expected) September 2022

- Guest lecturer:
 - · Workshop in Big Data and Machine Learning (M.Sc., Ph.D.) at Maynooth University, Spring 2022.
- Teaching Assistant:
 - Introduction to Microeconomics (M.Sc.), Fall 2021. Topics in Political Economy (M.Sc.), Fall 2019, 2020.
 - · Development Economics (M.Sc.), Spring 2020. · Emergence of Macroeconomic Policy (M.Sc.), Spring 2020.
 - · Long Run Development (M.Sc.), Fall 2019. · Introduction to Economic Policy A/B (B.Sc.), 2018-2019.
- Research Assistant.

SAS, May 2018 - August 2018

• Training Analytical Consultant: Organizing and delivering classes on SAS Base programming language.

Skills, Technologies and Languages

Research Skills:

 $\bullet \ \, {\rm Data \ management.} \ \, \bullet \ \, {\rm Data \ scraping.} \ \, \bullet \ \, {\rm Data \ visualization.} \ \, \bullet \ \, {\rm Micro-Econometrics.} \ \, {\rm Causal \ inference.} \ \, \bullet \ \, {\rm Machine \ Learning.}$

Soft Skills:

 $\cdot \ \, \text{Critical thinking.} \cdot \text{Problem solving.} \cdot \text{Detail-oriented.} \cdot \text{Independent/team-work.} \cdot \text{Good communication.} \cdot \text{Project management.}$

 $\textbf{Software} \colon STATA \text{ (fluent), Python, R (intermediate), SQL, QGIS, SAS, Office (basic)}.$

Languages: Italian (native), English (fluent).

Research Projects

Setting an example: political leaders' cues and health behavior in the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic in Mexico, with Bruno Morando and Luciano Ayala, Latin American Policy (2021)

- How do political leaders' cues affect citizen behavior regarding a new and complex issue?
- We combine local electoral and mobility data within the context of Mexico in the early stages of the Covid-19 pandemic.
- We exploit an event-study type of analysis. Citizens' geographic mobility in pro-government municipalities was higher than in cities where support for the president was less strong.

• Our results are driven by cities with higher TV and internet penetration.

Simultaneous elections and electoral outcomes: evidence from Italy

- I Investigate the impact that same day national-local elections have on the local electoral stage.
- I employ a difference-in-differences estimation design, comparing same-day and not same-day election, within the Italian context. Voters' participation, political participation and competition increase. Right local parties gain in term of local votes share.
- I then focus just on same day national-local elections only. A relevant % of municipalities prefers left (right) at the local level and right(left) at the national one. Voters behave as such to balance government's levels to then have balanced policies.

Organised crime, public procurement and firms, with Decio Coviello and Nicola Mastrorocco

- What is the impact of criminal organisations on the legal economy?
- We employ a difference-in-differences estimation design within the South-Italian setting. We exploit the staggered enforcement of a law that allows the national government to dissolve Mafia-colluded local governments.
- We combine highly detailed public procurement and firms balance sheet data.
- Cities colluded with the Mafia exhibit lower rebates and higher discretionary selection procedures. The results vary depending on the macro-procurement category considered and the party affiliation of the local colluded government.
- Firms that win public contracts in cities colluded with the Mafia exhibit higher profits.

Social capital and the power of mafia, with Francesca Calamunci

- What is the long-term effect of organized crime presence on social capital?
- We collect contemporary data that proxy for social capital, and historical measures of Mafia presence. We inspect two scenarios within the Italian landscape.
- First, we focus on the island of Sicily. We run linear and instrumental variable regressions. We find that the long-term exposure to the Mafia decreases the development of social capital.
- Second, we focus on the centre-north regions of Italy. We exploit a law that forced Mafia members to resettle in this macro-area. We find a set of mixed result that need further understanding.

Organised crime and human capital, within-city evidence from Italy

- What is the effect of organised crime on human capital?
- I investigate this question in the Italian setting, focusing on a set of cities with high prevalence of organised crime.
- I exploit OCR to measure from the DIA's maps the presence and the names of the gangs within this set of cities.
- I plan to exploit text analysis to re-construct the traditional presence of these gangs, as well as the level of competition within a district of a city.
- I plan to combine this novel dataset with human capital data from INVALSI, and estimate a difference-in-differences model. Preliminary Results coming soon!

Awards and Fellowships

Economics Department Scholarship, Trinity College Dublin, 2018-2020 2020 Government of Ireland Postgraduate Scholarship, Irish Research Council, 2020-present

Interests

Sports, with a particular interest on basketball and football. Travelling, videogames and playing guitar.

References

Prof. Nicola Mastrorocco (supervisor) Economics Department Trinity College Dublin n.mastrorocco@tcd.ie Prof. Gaia Narciso Economics Department Trinity College Dublin narcisog@tcd.ie